Guide to the Whitney Arms Company Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Whitney Arms Company papers
1862-1886
MS 618
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
Correspondence, financial papers, and miscellanea of the Whitney Arms Company of New Haven, Connecticut.
Whitney Arms Company
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the New Haven Water Company, 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The Whitney Arms Company was established in New Haven by Eli Whitney, who sought to create a more accurate musket, that would still be durable enough for use by soldiers. He located the plant on both sides of the Mill River. Though founded in 1798, operations were still small at the time of Whitney's death in 1825. The factory was eventually handed down to Whitney's son, Eli Whitney, Jr., who ran the company for much of the nineteenth century. In 1888, the Whitney Arms Company was sold to the Winchester Repeating Arms Company.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, financial papers, and miscellanea of the Whitney Arms Company of New Haven, Connecticut.
Business; Firearms, American; Manufactures -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Whitney Arms Company
- Inventory
  - Letterbooks (indexed)
    - 1862 Jun 20-1863 Feb 4 (Box 1)
    - 1863 Feb 4-1863 Aug 7 (Box 2)
    - 1878 Sep 24-1879 Jan 27 (Box 3)
    - 1882 May 12-1882 Nov 6 (Box 4)
    - 1883 Mar 5-1883 Sep 10 (Box 5)
    - 1885 Mar 19-1885 Aug 28 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1882-1884 (Box 7)
  - Checkbook stubs, 1886 (Box 7)
  - Three indexes to missing letterbooks, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous financial papers, undated (Box 7)